As an Indian, and now as a politician
كهندي والآن كسياسي،
and a government minister,
ووزير في الحكومة
I've become rather concerned about
أصبحت قلقا نوعا ما إزاء
the hype we're hearing about our own country,
الجدل الذي نسمعه عن بلادنا،
all this talk about India becoming a world leader,
كل هذا الحديث عن أن الهند أصبحت قائدة للعالم ،
even the next superpower.
قريبة حتى من أن تكون القوة العظمى القادمة.
In fact, the American publishers of my book,
في الواقع، الناشرون الأمريكيون لكتابي،
"The Elephant, The Tiger and the Cell Phone,"
"الفيل، النمر، والتلفون الخلوي"،
added a gratuitous subtitle saying,
أضافوا عنوانا فرعيا سخيا يقول،
"India: The next 21st-century power."
"الهند: القوى القادمة للقرن الواحد والعشرين".
And I just don't think that's what India's all about,
و أنا لا أعتقد أن هذا هو كل ما هي عليه الهند،
or should be all about.
أو المفروض أن تكونه.
Indeed, what worries me is the entire notion of world leadership
بالفعل، ما يقلقني هو كل هذا الاعتقاد بمفهوم قيادة العالم
seems to me terribly archaic.
الذي يبدو لي بالٍ بشكل كبير.
It's redolent of James Bond movies
إن له صيت أفلام جيمس بوند
and Kipling ballads.
و أغاني كيبلينج الشعبية
After all, what constitutes a world leader?
بالنهاية، ما الذي يشكل قائداً عالمياً؟
If it's population, we're on course to top the charts.
إذا كان الأمر بعدد السكان، فنحن في الطريق إلى رأس القائمة.
We will overtake China by 2034.
سوف نتجاوز الصين في عام 2034.
Is it military strength? Well, we have the world's fourth largest army.
هل هي القوة العسكرية ؟ حسنا، نحن لدينا رابع أكبر جيش في العالم.
Is it nuclear capacity? We know we have that.
هل هي بالقدرة النووية ؟ نحن نعلم أنّا لدينا ذلك.
The Americans have even recognized it,
حتى أن الأمريكان قد اعترفوا بهذا،
in an agreement.
في إتفاقية.
Is it the economy? Well, we have now
هل هو الاقتصاد ؟ نحن لدينا الآن،
the fifth-largest economy in the world
خامس أضخم اقتصاد في العالم
in purchasing power parity terms.
من حيث تعادل القوة الشرائية.
And we continue to grow. When the rest of the world took a beating last year,
ونحن نواصل النمو. عندما عانى بقية العالم من التراجع في العام الماضي،
we grew at 6.7 percent.
كنا قد نمونا بنسبة 6.7 بالمئة.
But, somehow, none of that adds up to me,
لكن، بطريقة ما، ليست هذه أسباب اعتقادي،
to what I think India really can aim to contribute in the world,
بأن الهند بإمكانها فعلا الإسهام في العالم،
in this part of the 21st century.
في هذه الفترة من القرن الواحد والعشرين.
And so I wondered, could
ولذلك تساءلت، هل
what the future beckons for India to be all about
ما يومئ إليه المستقبل عن ماهية الهند
be a combination of these things allied to something else,
هو أن تكون مزيجا من هذه الأشياء متحالفة مع شيء آخر،
the power of example,
قوة القدوة،
the attraction of India's culture,
جاذبية حضارة الهند،
what, in other words, people like to call "soft power."
الذي، بمسمى آخر، يطلق عليه الناس "القوة الناعمة".
Soft power is a concept invented by a Harvard academic,
القوة الناعمة هي مفهوم إخترعه أكاديمي في هارفارد،
Joseph Nye, a friend of mine.
جوزيف ناي، أحد أصدقائي.
And, very simply, and I'm really cutting it short because of the time limits here,
وأنا، بشكل مبسط، أعرفه بإختصار بسبب عامل الوقت،
it's essentially the ability of a country to attract others
هو بشكل أساسي قدرة الدولة على جذب الآخرين
because of its culture, its political values,
بفعل ثقافتها، وقيمها السياسية،
its foreign policies.
وسياساتها الخارجية.
And, you know, lots of countries do this. He was writing initially about the States,
وتعلمون، العديد من الدول تملك هذا. هو كان في الأصل يكتب عن الولايات،
but we know the Alliance Francaise
لكننا نعرف الأتحاد الفرنسي
is all about French soft power, the British Council.
يمثل القوة الفرنسية الناعمة، المجلس الثقافي البريطاني.
The Beijing Olympics were an exercise in Chinese soft power.
أولمبياد بكين كان مثالا على القوة الناعمة الصينية.
Americans have the Voice of America and the Fulbright scholarships.
لدى الأمريكيون إذاعة صوت أمريكا وبرنامج فولبرايت للمنح الدراسية.
But, the fact is, in fact,
ولكن الواقع هو، في الحقيقة،
that probably Hollywood and MTV and McDonalds
أن هوليوود وإم تي في وماكدونالدز على الأغلب
have done more for American soft power
قد خدموا قوة أمريكا الناعمة
around the world than any specifically government activity.
حول العالم أكثر من أي نشاط حكومي خاص.
So soft power is something that really emerges
إذن القوى الناعمة تنطلق فعلا
partly because of governments,
بشكل جزئي على يد الحكومات،
but partly despite governments.
ولكن جزئيا برغم نشاط هذه الحكومات.
And in the information era we all live in today,
وفي عصر المعلومات الذي نعيش كلنا فيه اليوم،
what we might call the TED age,
والذي بإمكاننا أن نسميه حقبة تيد "TED"،
I'd say that countries are increasingly being judged
يمكنني القول أنه يتم تقييم الحكومات بشكل متزايد
by a global public that's been fed
من قبل الجمهور العالمي الذي يُغذى
on an incessant diet of Internet news,
بسيل متواصل من أخبار الإنترنت،
of televised images,
من الصور التلفزيونية،
of cellphone videos, of email gossip.
من مقاطع الفيديو على التلفونات الخلوية، من الإشاعات التي ينقلها البريد الإلكتروني،
In other words, all sorts of communication devices
بمعنى آخر; كل أنواع أجهزة الإتصال
are telling us the stories of countries,
تخبرنا قصصا عن الدول
whether or not the countries concerned want people to hear those stories.
سواء كانت هذه الدول تهتم بما تقوله عنها هذه القصص أم لا.
Now, in this age, again, countries with access
والآن، كما قلت في هذا الزمن، الدول التي لها قابلية للوصول
to multiple channels of communication
لمختلف قنوات الاتصال
and information have a particular advantage.
والمعلومات لديها ميزة لصالحها.
And of course they have more influence, sometimes, about how they're seen.
وبالطبع لديها تأثير أكثر على الطريقة التي تبدو بها هذه الدول.
India has more all-news TV channels
الهند لديها قنوات إخبارية أكثر
than any country in the world,
من أي دولة أخرى في العالم،
in fact in most of the countries in this part of the world put together.
أو للحقيقة أكثر من كل الدول في هذا الجزء من العالم مجتمعة مع بعضها.
But, the fact still is that it's not just that.
ولكن، تظل الحقيقة أن هذا ليس كل شيء.
In order to have soft power, you have to be connected.
ليكون لديك قوة ناعمة لابد أن تكون متصلا.
One might argue that India has become
قد يناقش شخص ما أن الهند قد أصبحت
an astonishingly connected country.
دولة متصلة بشكل مذهل.
I think you've already heard the figures.
أعتقد أنكم قد سمعتم مسبقا الاحصاءات.
We've been selling 15 million cellphones a month.
أصبحنا في الهند نبيع معدل 15 مليون هاتف خلوي في الشهر.
Currently there are 509 million cellphones
في الهند، حاليا يوجد 509 مليون هاتف خلوي
in Indian hands, in India.
بين أيدٍ هندية.
And that makes us larger than the U.S. as a telephone market.
وهذا يجعل منّا سوق أكبر للهواتف من الولايات المتحدة.
In fact, those 15 million cellphones
في الواقع، هذه الخمسة عشر مليون هاتف خلوي
are the most connections that any country,
هي كم الإتصالات التي أي دولة،
including the U.S. and China,
بما فيها الولايات المتحدة والصين،
has ever established in the history of telecommunications.
قامت بإنشائها منذ بدء تاريخ الاتصالات الهاتفية.
But, what perhaps some of you don't realize
ولكن، البعض منكم قد لا يدرك
is how far we've come to get there.
كم العناء الذي تكبدناه لنصل لهذا المستوى.
You know, when I grew up in India,
عندما نشأت في الهند،
telephones were a rarity.
كانت الهواتف في غاية الندرة.
In fact, they were so rare that elected members of Parliament
في الحقيقة، كانوا من من الندرة لدرجة أن الأعضاء المنتخبين في البرلمان
had the right to allocate 15 telephone lines
كان لديهم الحق في منح 15 خط هاتفي
as a favor to those they deemed worthy.
كمكافأة لأولئك الذين يرون أنهم يستحقونها.
If you were lucky enough to be a wealthy businessman
إذا كنت محظوظا بما فيه الكفاية لتكون رجل أعمال غني
or an influential journalist, or a doctor or something, you might have a telephone.
أو صحفي مؤثر، أو طبيب، أو شيء من هذا القبيل، قد تحصل على هاتف.
But sometimes it just sat there.
ولكن، بعض الأوقات يبقى هذا الهاتف صامتا.
I went to high school in Calcutta.
لقد ذهبت للمدرسة الثانوية في كالكتا.
And we would look at this instrument sitting in the front foyer.
وكنا نجلس ونترقب هذا الجهاز الموضوع في البهو الأمامي.
But half the time we would pick it up
وفي نصف المرات كنا نلتقط السماعة
with an expectant look on our faces,
ونظرة الترقب على وجوهنا،
there would be no dial tone.
ولم يكن هناك نغمة اتصال.
If there was a dial tone and you dialed a number,
لو كانت نغمة الاتصال موجودة وطلبت رقما،
the odds were two in three you wouldn't get the number you were intending to reach.
الاحتمال هو أن مرتين من كل ثلاث مرات لن تحصل على الرقم الذي طلبته.
In fact the words "wrong number" were more popular than the word "Hello."
في الحقيقة عبارة "الرقم خاطئ" كانت أكثر شيوعا من كلمة "الو".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If you then wanted to connect to another city,
وفيما لو أردت الاتصال بمدينة أخرى،
let's say from Calcutta you wanted to call Delhi,
دعنا نقول من كالكتا أردت الاتصال بدلهي،
you'd have to book something called a trunk call,
كان لابد من أن تحجز موعدا لما يسمى بمكالمة رئيسية،
and then sit by the phone all day, waiting for it to come through.
ومن ثم تجلس طوال اليوم بجانب الهاتف، تنتظر هذه المكالمة لتتم.
Or you could pay eight times the going rate
أو بإمكانك أن تدفع ثمان أضعاف سعر الاتصال
for something called a lightning call.
لمكالمة تسمى مكالمة برق.
But, lightning struck rather slowly in our country in those days,
لكن البرق كان يومض ببطء في بلادنا تلك الأيام،
so, it was like about a half an hour for a lightning call to come through.
إذن، كانت مكالمة البرق تحتاج لنصف ساعة لتتم.
In fact, so woeful was our telephone service
في الحقيقة، كانت خدمات الهاتف من البؤس
that a Member of Parliament stood up in 1984 and complained about this.
بحيث أن عضوا من البرلمان تقدم في عام 1984 واشتكى بخصوص هذا.
And the Then-Communications Minister replied in a lordly manner
وحينها رد عليه وزير الاتصالات بلهجة استعلائية
that in a developing country
أنه في دولة نامية
communications are a luxury, not a right,
الاتصالات رفاهية وليست حقا من الحقوق،
that the government had no obligation to provide better service,
بحيث أن الحكومة ليست ملزمة لتقدم خدمة أفضل،
and if the honorable Member wasn't satisfied with his telephone,
وأنه إذا كان سيادة العضو ليس راضيا عن هاتفه،
could he please return it, since there was an eight-year-long waiting list
هل له لطفا أن يعيده، بما أن مدة الانتظار للحصول على هاتف في الهند
for telephones in India.
تصل إلى ثمان سنوات.
Now, fast-forward to today and this is what you see:
الآن، نظرة على زمننا الحالي، وهذا ما تراه،
the 15 million cell phones a month.
الخمسة عشرة مليون هاتف خلوي في الشهر.
But what is most striking is who is carrying those cell phones.
ولكن الملفت للانتباه هو من هم الذين يستخدمون هذه الهواتف الخلوية.
You know, if you visit friends in the suburbs of Delhi,
تعلمون، إذا زرتم أصدقاءكم في ضواحي دلهي،
on the side streets you will find a fellow with a cart
على جوانب الطرق ستجدون شخصا مع عربة
that looks like it was designed in the 16th century,
تبدو كما لو أنها صممت في القرن السادس عشر،
wielding a coal-fired steam iron
يكوي فيها الملابس باستخدام مكواة بخارية تعمل على الفحم
that might have been invented in the 18th century.
والتي ربما كانت قد اخترعت في القرن الثامن عشر.
He's called an isthri wala. But he's carrying a 21st-century instrument.
هو يسمى اسثري والا (الولد المكوجي). لكنه يحمل جهازا من القرن الواحد والعشرين.
He's carrying a cell phone because most incoming calls are free,
هو يحمل هاتفا خلويا لأن أغلب المكالمات الواردة مجانية،
and that's how he gets orders from the neighborhood,
لذا هو يتلقى الطلبات من العملاء بالجوار،
to know where to collect clothes to get them ironed.
ليخبروه من أين يجمع الملابس التي يريدونه أن يكويها.
The other day I was in Kerala, my home state,
في أحد الأيام كنت في كيرلا، الولاية التي هي مسقط رأسي،
at the country farm of a friend,
في مزرعة ريفية يملكها أحد أصدقائي،
about 20 kilometers away from any place you'd consider urban.
تبعد مسافة 20 كيلومترا عن أي منطقة يمكنكم اعتبارها مدينة.
And it was a hot day and he said, "Hey, would you like some fresh coconut water?"
ولأنه كان يوما حارا هو قال، "هل ترغب ببعض ماء جوز الهند الطازج؟"
And it's the best thing and the most nutritious and refreshing thing you can drink
وهو أكثر مشروب منعش ومغذٍ يمكنك شربه
on a hot day in the tropics, so I said sure.
في يوم حار في المناطق الإستوائية، لذا أنا قلت بالتأكيد.
And he whipped out his cellphone, dialed the number,
للفور أخرج هاتفه الخلوي، طلب رقما،
and a voice said, "I'm up here."
وصوت قال، "أنا هناك بالأعلى".
And right on top of the nearest coconut tree,
على أعلى شجرة جوز هند قريبة،
with a hatchet in one hand and a cell phone in the other,
مع منجل في يد وهاتف خلوي في اليد الأخرى
was a local toddy tapper,
كان هناك جامع العصير المحلي،
who proceeded to bring down the coconuts for us to drink.
والذي نزل فيما بعد وأحضر جوز الهند لنا لنشربه.
Fishermen are going out to sea and carrying their cell phones.
صائدو الأسماك يخرجون للبحر حاملين هواتفهم الخلوية.
When they catch the fish they call all the market towns along the coast
عندما يصطادون السمك هم يتصلون بكل الأسواق على امتداد الشاطىء
to find out where they get the best possible prices.
ليستفسروا أين يمكنهم الحصول على أفضل الأسعار لمحصولهم.
Farmers now, who used to have to spend half a day of backbreaking labor
المزارعون الآن، الذين كانوا يمضون نصف يوم من العمل المضني
to find out if the market town was open,
ليعرفوا ما إذا كان السوق مفتوحا،
if the market was on,
إذا ما كان المزاد قائما،
whether the product they'd harvested could be sold, what price they'd fetch.
وما إذا كانت المنتجات التي حصدوها ستبيع، حسب السعر الذي يرغبونه.
They'd often send an eight year old boy all the way on this trudge
كانوا غالبا ما يرسلون فتى في الثامنة ليقوم بكل هذه الرحلة المجهدة
to the market town to get that information and come back,
للسوق المحلي ليستقصي المعلومات ثم يعود لهم،
then they'd load the cart.
ليقوموا بعدها بتحميل عرباتهم.
Today they're saving half a day's labor with a two minute phone call.
اليوم هم يختصرون نصف يوم من العمل في مكالمة هاتفية لاتتجاوز الدقيقتين.
So this empowerment of the underclass
إذن هذا التمكين للطبقة الفقيرة
is the real result of India being connected.
هو الناتج الحقيقي من كون الهند أصبحت متصلة.
And that transformation is part of where India is heading today.
وهذا التحول هو جزء من التطور الذي الهند متجهة له حاليا.
But, of course that's not the only thing about India that's spreading.
ولكن، بالطبع ليس هذا هو الشيء الوحيد في الهند الذي يتسارع.
You've got Bollywood. My attitude to Bollywood is best summarized
هناك بوليوود. وموقفي من بوليوود يلخصه بشكل أفضل
in the tale of the two goats at a Bollywood garbage dump --
قصة اثنتين من الماعز في مرمى للنفايات في بوليوود --
Mr. Shekhar Kapur, forgive me --
سيد شيخار كابور، أستميحك عذرا --
and they're chewing away on cans of celluloid discarded by a Bollywood studio.
وكانتا تمضغان علب الأشرطة السينمائية التي ألقاها استوديو في بوليوود.
And the first goat, chewing away, says, "You know, this film is not bad."
والمعزة الأولى قالت، "تعلمين، هذا الفيلم ليس سيئا".
And the second goat says, "No, the book was better."
والأخرى قالت، "لا، الكتاب كان أفضل من الفيلم".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I usually tend to think that the book is usually better,
غالبا ما أميل للإعتقاد أن الكتاب دائما أفضل،
but, having said that,
ولكن، بقول هذا،
the fact is that Bollywood is now
الحقيقة أن بوليوود الآن
taking a certain aspect of Indian-ness and Indian culture around the globe,
مسؤولة عن جوانب معينة من شيوع الثقافة الهندية حول العالم،
not just in the Indian diaspora in the U.S. and the U.K.,
وليس فقط لدى الجالية الهندية في الولايات المتحدة والمملكة المتحدة،
but to the screens of Arabs and Africans, of Senegalese and Syrians.
ولكن أيضا على شاشات العرب والأفارقة، من السنغاليين إلى السوريين.
I've met a young man in New York whose illiterate mother
لقد قابلت شابا في نيويورك أمه غير متعلمة
in a village in Senegal
تعيش في قرية في السنغال
takes a bus once a month to the capital city of Dakar,
تأخذ الباص مرة كل شهر للعاصمة داكار،
just to watch a Bollywood movie.
فقط لتشاهد فيلم بوليوود.
She can't understand the dialogue.
هي لا يمكنها فهم الحوار.
She's illiterate, so she can't read the French subtitles.
هي أميّة، فلا يمكنها قراءة الترجمة الفرنسية.
But these movies are made to be understood despite such handicaps,
لكن، هذه الأفلام صنعت لتفهم بغض النظر عن هذه العوائق،
and she has a great time in the song and the dance and the action.
هي تستمتع بالأغاني والرقصات والمغامرة،
She goes away with stars in her eyes about India, as a result.
وتعود للمنزل ولديها صورة حالمة عن الهند، كنتيجة.
And this is happening more and more.
وهذا ينتشر أكثر فأكثر.
Afghanistan, we know what a serious security problem
أفغانستان، نعلم أي مشكلة أمنية حقيقية
Afghanistan is for so many of us in the world.
تشكلها أفغانستان بالنسبة للكثير من أنحاء العالم.
India doesn't have a military mission there.
الهند ليس لديها قوات عسكرية هناك.
You know what was India's biggest asset in Afghanistan in the last seven years?
ولكن تعلمون ماذا كان أكبر حليف للهند في أفغانستان خلال السبع سنوات الأخيرة؟
One simple fact:
حقيقة بسيطة:
you couldn't try to call an Afghan at 8:30 in the evening.
لا يمكنك أن تجرب الاتصال بأفغاني في الثامنة والنصف مساء.
Why? Because that was the moment
لماذا؟ لأنه كان الوقت الذي
when the Indian television soap opera,
الدراما الهندية التلفزيونية،
"Kyunki Saas Bhi Kabhi Bahu Thi," dubbed into Dari, was telecast on Tolo T.V.
[اسم المسلسل بالهندي]، مدبلجة للغة الأفغانية، تذاع على قناة تلفزيون تودو.
And it was the most popular television show in Afghan history.
وهي تعتبر أكثر عرض تلفزيوني يحظى بالمتابعة في التاريخ الأفغاني.
Every Afghan family wanted to watch it.
كل العائلات الأفغانية ترغب في مشاهدته.
They had to suspend functions at 8:30.
وكان عليهم أن يعطلوا كل أنشطتهم في الثامنة والنصف.
Weddings were reported to be interrupted
كان يحكى أن الزواجات تتوقف مؤقتا
so guests could cluster around the T.V. set,
ليتمكن المدعوون من التجمهر حول التلفاز،
and then turn their attention back to the bride and groom.
وحينما تنتهي الحلقة يعود الاهتمام مجددا للعروس والعريس.
Crime went up at 8:30. I have read a Reuters dispatch --
نسب الجريمة ارتفعت في الثامنة والنصف. كما كنت اقرأ في تقرير إخباري من رويترز --
so this is not Indian propaganda, a British news agency --
وإذن هذه ليست حملة دعائية هندية، هذه وكالة أخبار بريطانية --
about how robbers in the town of Musarri Sharif*
عن كيف أن اللصوص في مدينة مزار الشريف
stripped a vehicle of its windshield wipers,
نزعوا مساحات الزجاج الأمامي من إحدى السيارات،
its hubcaps, its sideview mirrors,
أغطية الإطارات، والمرايا الجانبية،
any moving part they could find, at 8:30,
كل ما أمكنهم نزعه من السيارة في الثامنة والنصف،
because the watchmen were busy watching the T.V. rather than minding the store.
مستغلين أن الحرس (النواطير) مشغولون بمشاهدة المسلسل بدلا من مراقبة المحل.
And they scrawled on the windshield in a reference to the show's heroine,
وقد خربشوا على زجاج السيارة الأمامي في عبارة عن بطلة المسلسل،
"Tulsi Zindabad": "Long live Tulsi."
"تعيش تولسي".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's soft power. And that is what India is developing
هذه هي القوة الناعمة، هذا ما تطوره الهند
through the "E" part of TED:
من جزئية E في TED: (الترفيه)
its own entertainment industry.
صناعة الترفيه الخاصة بالهند.
The same is true, of course -- we don't have time for too many more examples --
وهذا بالطبع ينطبق -- لا نملك الكثير من الوقت لمزيد من الأمثلة --
but it's true of our music, of our dance,
لكنه ينطبق على الموسيقى الخاصة بنا، على رقصاتنا،
of our art, yoga, ayurveda, even Indian cuisine.
على فنوننا، اليوقا، الايروفيدا (الطب الهندي القديم)، وحتى المطبخ الهندي.
I mean, the proliferation of Indian restaurants
أعني، الإنتشار الواسع للمطاعم الهندية
since I first went abroad as a student, in the mid '70s,
منذ سافرت أول مرة للخارج كمبتعث، في منتصف السبعينات،
and what I see today, you can't go to a mid-size town in Europe or North America
وما أراه اليوم، لا يمكنكم الذهاب لأي مدينة متوسطة الحجم في أوروبا أو أمريكا الشمالية
and not find an Indian restaurant. It may not be a very good one.
ولا تجدوا فيها مطعما هنديا. قد لا يكون مطعما ممتازا.
But, today in Britain, for example,
ولكن، اليوم في بريطانيا، كمثال،
Indian restaurants in Britain
المطاعم الهندية في بريطانيا
employ more people than the coal mining,
توظف عددا أكبر من الأشخاص العاملين في تنجيم الفحم،
ship building and iron and steel industries combined.
صناعة السفن، والتعدين مجتمعين.
So the empire can strike back.
إذن هذا هدف في مرمى الإمبراطورية (البريطانية وكأنه يتحدث عن استعمار معكوس).
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But, with this increasing awareness of India,
ولكن، مع هذا الاهتمام المتزايد بالهند،
with you and with I, and so on,
منك ومني،
with tales like Afghanistan,
مع قصص مثل هذه القادمة من أفغانستان،
comes something vital in the information era,
يأتي شيء حيوي في زمن المعلومات،
the sense that in today's world
الشعور أنه في عالم اليوم
it's not the side of the bigger army that wins,
ليست الجيوش الأكبر هي التي تنتصر،
it's the country that tells a better story that prevails.
إنها الدول التي تحكي حكايا أفضل هي التي تتسيد.
And India is, and must remain, in my view, the land of the better story.
والهند كانت، وستظل، في إعتقادي، بلد القصص الأفضل.
Stereotypes are changing. I mean, again, having gone to the U.S.
الأحكام النمطية آخذة في التغير. أعني، مجددا كوني ذهبت للولايات المتحدة
as a student in the mid '70s,
كطالب في منتصف السبعينات،
I knew what the image of India was then, if there was an image at all.
أعرف ما الصورة التي كانت تبدو عليها الهند إن كان هناك أي صورة نمطية من الأساس.
Today, people in Silicon Valley and elsewhere
اليوم، الناس في وادي السيليكون التقني وفي أماكن أخر
speak of the IITs, the Indian Institutes of Technology
يتحدثون عن IIT، المعهد الهندي للتقنية
with the same reverence they used to accord to MIT.
بنفس التبجيل الذي كان يتردد عن MIT معهد ماساتشوستس للتقنية.
This can sometimes have unintended consequences. OK.
وهذا أحيانا يجلب تبعات غير مألوفة.
I had a friend, a history major like me,
كان لدي صديق، تخصص في التاريخ مثلي،
who was accosted at Schiphol Airport in Amsterdam,
كان قد خوطب في مطار سكيفول في أمستردام،
by an anxiously perspiring European saying,
من قبل شخص أوروبي محتار قائلا له،
"You're Indian, you're Indian! Can you help me fix my laptop?"
"أنت هندي، أوه أنت هندي! هلا ساعدتني في إصلاح حاسوبي الشخصي المعطل؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We've gone from the image of India as
لقد انتقلنا من صورة الهند
land of fakirs lying on beds of nails,
كأرض للدراويش المستلقين على أسرة من المسامير،
and snake charmers with the Indian rope trick,
والسحرة الذين يراقصون الثعابين باستخدام حيلة الحبل الهندية،
to the image of India as a land of mathematical geniuses,
إلى صورة الهند كأرض لعباقرة الرياضيات،
computer wizards, software gurus.
وسحرة (عرافي) الحاسوب، ومعلمي البرامج.
But that too is transforming the Indian story around the world.
هذا أيضا يحول الحكاية الهندية حول العالم.
But, there is something more substantive to that.
ولكن، هناك جانب أكثر ثباتا في كل هذا.
The story rests on a fundamental platform
هذه الحكاية بنيت على أساس صلب
of political pluralism.
من التعددية السياسية.
It's a civilizational story to begin with.
هي حكاية التمدن قبل كل شيء آخر.
Because India has been an open society for millennia.
لأن الهند كانت المجتمع الأكثر انفتاحا طوال الألفية.
India gave refuge to the Jews, fleeing the destruction of the first temple
الهند منحوا الملاجيء لليهود، الذي هربوا من هدم أول معبد
by the Babylonians, and said thereafter by the Romans.
على يد البابليين، والذي استمر بعدها على يد الرومان.
In fact, legend has is that when Doubting Thomas, the Apostle, Saint Thomas,
في الحقيقية، تقول الأسطورة أن القديس الحائر توماس، أحد حواريي المسيح،
landed on the shores of Kerala, my home state,
عندما رسى على شواطىء كيرلا، ولايتي،
somewhere around 52 A.D.,
قرابة السنة الثانية والخمسين بعد الميلاد،
he was welcomed on shore by a flute-playing Jewish girl.
رحبت به على الشاطىء فتاة يهودية كانت تعزف الفلوت.
And to this day remains the only Jewish diaspora
ولهذا اليوم تظل جالية اليهود في الهند
in the history of the Jewish people, which has never encountered
منذ بداية كل تاريخ اليهود، الوحيدين الذين لم يتعرضوا
a single incident of anti-semitism.
لحادث واحد من معاداة السامية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
That's the Indian story.
هذه هي الحكاية الهندية.
Islam came peacefully to the south,
الإسلام حل بسلام في الجنوب،
slightly more differently complicated history in the north.
ربما انتشر بتاريخ أكثر تعقيدا نوعا ما في الشمال.
But all of these religions have found a place and a welcome home in India.
ولكن، كل هذه الأديان وجدت في الهند أرضا مرحبة.
You know, we just celebrated, this year, our general elections,
تعلمون، للتو احتفلنا، هذا العام، بالانتخابات العامة،
the biggest exercise in democratic franchise in human history.
أكبر تطبيق لممارسة الديموقراطية وحقوق الانتخاب في تاريخ البشرية.
And the next one will be even bigger, because our voting population
والانتخابات القادمة ستكون أكبر حتى، لأن المنتخبين
keeps growing by 20 million a year.
سيستمرون في التزايد بمعدل عشرين مليون في السنة.
But, the fact is
ولكن، الواقع هو
that the last elections, five years ago,
أن الانتخابات السابقة، منذ خمس سنوات مضت،
gave the world extraordinary phenomenon
أعطت العالم مثالا على ظاهرة غير معتادة
of an election being won by a woman political leader
لانتخاب تكسبه قائدة سياسية
of Italian origin and Roman Catholic faith, Sonia Gandhi,
من أصل إيطالي وتدين بالكاثوليكية الرومانية، سونيا غاندي،
who then made way for a Sikh, Mohan Singh,
تنحت جانبا لأجل سيخي، موهان سينغ (رئيس الوزراء الحالي)،
to be sworn in as Prime Minister
لينصب كرئيس للوزراء،
by a Muslim, President Abdul Kalam,
من قبل رئيس دولة مسلم، الرئيس عبدالكلام،
in a country 81 percent Hindu.
في دولة 81 منها هندوس.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This is India, and of course it's all the more striking
هذه هي الهند، وبالطبع كل هذا مذهل أكثر
because it was four years later that we all applauded
لأننا بعد هذا بأربع سنوات صفقنا اعجابا
the U.S., the oldest democracy in the modern world,
للولايات المتحدة، صاحبة أقدم ديموقراطية في العالم الحديث،
more than 220 years of free and fair elections,
والتي تملك تاريخا من 220 عام من الانتخابات الحرة والعادلة،
which took till last year to elect a president or a vice president
والتي فقط للتو في السنة الماضية استطاعت انتخاب رئيس أو نائب رئيس،
who wasn't white, male or Christian.
لم يكن أبيض اللون، رجل، أو مسيحي.
So, maybe -- oh sorry, he is Christian, I beg your pardon --
إذن ربما، -- أوه آسف، هو مسيحي، أستميحكم عذرا --
and he is male, but he isn't white.
أقصد أنه كان رجل، ومسيحي، لكنه لم يكن أبيض (الرئيس باراك أوباما).
All the others have been all those three.
كل الرؤساء السابقين كان لابد أن يكونوا كل هذه الثلاث أشياء (رجال، مسيحيون، بيض).
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
All his predecessors have been all those three,
كل سابقيه كانوا يحملون هذه الثلاث صفات،
and that's the point I was trying to make.
هذه هي النقطة التي كنت أحاول صنعها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But, the issue is
ولكن، القضية هي
that when I talked about that example,
أنني عندما تحدثت عن هذا المثال،
it's not just about talking about India, it's not propaganda.
هو ليس فقط للتحدث بدعائية وترويج عن الهند.
Because ultimately, that electoral outcome
لأن بالنهاية، نتائج الانتخابات
had nothing to do with the rest of the world.
لا علاقة له بباقي العالم.
It was essentially India being itself.
هي بدت هكذا لأنها انعكاس للهند نفسها.
And ultimately, it seems to me,
وبشكل عام، كما يبدو لي،
that always works better than propaganda.
هذه أمثلة تنشر صورة أفضل من الحملات الدعائية.
Governments aren't very good at telling stories.
الحكومات ليست بالجيدة في رواية القصص.
But people see a society for what it is,
لكن الناس ينظرون للمجتمع كما هو وعلى حقيقته،
and that, it seems to me, is what ultimately
وهذا، ما أراه،
will make a difference in today's information era,
يصنع الفرق في عصر المعلومات الحالي،
in today's TED age.
في زمن TED الحالي.
So India now is no longer
إذن الهند لم تعد
the nationalism of ethnicity or language or religion,
القومية القادمة من عرق إثني معين أو لغة أو دين،
because we have every ethnicity known to mankind, practically,
لأننا عمليا، لدينا جميع الإثنيات التي عرفتها البشرية،
we've every religion know to mankind,
وكل الأديان التي اعتنقتها البشرية،
with the possible exception of Shintoism,
ربما الاستثناء الوحيد هو الديانة الشنتوية (لا معلومات عن تواجدها في الهند).
though that has some Hindu elements somewhere.
رغم كونها كديانة تملك بعض العناصر الهندوسية بشكل ما.
We have 23 official languages that are recognized in our Constitution.
لدينا 23 لغة رسمية يقرها دستورنا.
And those of you who cashed your money here
وأولئك منكم الذين حصلوا على صرف نقدي هنا
might be surprised to see how many scripts there are
ربما تفاجئتم حينما رأيتم كم هو عدد الكتابات الموجودة
on the rupee note, spelling out the denominations.
على ورقة نقد الروبية، تستهدف جميع الطوائف بلغتهم.
We've got all of that.
لدينا هذا كله.
We don't even have geography uniting us,
رغم أنه أصلا لا توجد جغرافية توحد بيننا.
because the natural geography of the subcontinent
لأن الجغرافيا الطبيعية لشبه القارة
framed by the mountains and the sea was hacked
والذي تحدده الجبال والبحر كانت قد اخترقت
by the partition with Pakistan in 1947.
بإنفصال باكستان عن الهند في 1947.
In fact, you can't even take the name of the country for granted,
في الحقيقة، لا يمكنك حتى التسليم باسم البلد كشيء معروف.
because the name "India" comes from the river Indus,
لأن الاسم "الهند" أتى من النهر اندوس،
which flows in Pakistan.
الذي يجري أصلا في باكستان لا الهند.
But, the whole point is that India
لكن النقطة بأجملها هي أن الهند
is the nationalism of an idea.
هي قومية مبنية على فكرة.
It's the idea of an ever-ever-land,
فكرة أرض الجميع،
emerging from an ancient civilization,
التي انبثقت من الحضارات القديمة،
united by a shared history,
والتي وحدها تاريخ مشترك،
but sustained, above all, by pluralist democracy.
ولكن استمرارها مرتبط، قبل كل شيء، بديموقراطية تعددية.
That is a 21st-century story as well as an ancient one.
هذه قصة من القرن الواحد والعشرين مثلما أنها قصة قديمة.
And it's the nationalism of an idea that
وهذه القومية الفكرية هي التي بشكل أساسي تعني
essentially says you can endure differences of caste, creed,
أنك تستطيع مواجهة الإختلافات في الطائفة، العقيدة،
color, culture, cuisine, custom and costume, consonant, for that matter,
اللون، الثقافة، الطعام، العادات والتقاليد، الثوابت إن شئتم،
and still rally around a consensus.
ولكنها لا تزال تتوحد على الإتفاق في الرأي.
And the consensus is of a very simple principle,
وهذا الإتفاق هو في مبدأ بسيط جدا،
that in a diverse plural democracy like India
وهو أنه في ديموقراطية تعددية مثل الهند
you don't really have to agree on everything all the time,
لا يجب فعلا أن توافق على كل التفاصيل كل الوقت،
so long as you agree on the ground rules
مادمت توافق على القواعد العريضة
of how you will disagree.
لكيفية عدم الاتفاق.
The great success story of India,
قصة نجاح الهند الكبرى،
a country that so many learned scholars and journalists
الدولة التي باحثون وصحفيون كثر
assumed would disintegrate, in the '50s and '60s,
توقعوا أنها ستُحل في الخمسينات والستينات،
is that it managed to maintain consensus on how to survive without consensus.
تتمثل في أنها تمكنت من الحفاظ على الاتفاق على المضي كدولة دون اتفاق.
Now, that is the India that is emerging into the 21st century.
هذه هي الهند التي ستنطلق نحو القرن الواحد والعشرين.
And I do want to make the point
وما أريد أن أوضحه كنقطة
that if there is anything worth celebrating about India,
هو أنه إذا كان هناك ما يستحق الإحتفاء به في الهند،
it isn't military muscle, economic power.
فهو ليس القوى العسكرية ولا الاقتصادية.
All of that is necessary,
كل هذه القوى مهمة،
but we still have huge amounts of problems to overcome.
لكن مازال هناك الكثير من الصعوبات لنتجاوزها.
Somebody said we are super poor, and we are also super power.
شخص ما قال أننا الفقر الأعظم مثلما أننا القوة العظمى.
We can't really be both of those.
لا يمكننا فعلا أن نكون هذين الشيئين في الوقت نفسه.
We have to overcome our poverty. We have to deal with the
لا بد أن نتخطى الفقر. لا بد لنا أن نتعاطى مع
hardware of development,
صعوبات وتحديات التنمية،
the ports, the roads, the airports,
الموانىء، الطرق، المطارات،
all the infrastructural things we need to do,
كل البنى التحتية التي نحتاج العمل عليها،
and the software of development,
وأيضا "برمجيات" التنمية (الأشياء الغير مادية)،
the human capital, the need for the ordinary person in India
الموارد البشرية، حاجة الفرد العادي في الهند
to be able to have a couple of square meals a day,
لأن يكون قادرا على الحصول على مأوى وقوت يومه،
to be able to send his or her children
أن يكون قادرا على إرسال أطفاله
to a decent school,
لمدرسة مرموقة،
and to aspire to work a job
ولأن يتطلع للعمل في وظيفة
that will give them opportunities in their lives
ستمنح هؤلاء الأطفال فرصا كافية في حياتهم
that can transform themselves.
ليتمكنوا من تحويل حياتهم للأفضل.
But, it's all taking place, this great adventure of conquering those challenges,
ولكن، كل هذا يجري حاليا، هذه المغامرة الضخمة للتغلب على هذه التحديات،
those real challenges which none of us can pretend don't exist.
كل التحديات الحقيقية التي لا يمكننا الإدعاء أنها غير موجودة.
But, it's all taking place in an open society,
ولكن كل هذا السعي يجري في مجتمع منفتح،
in a rich and diverse and plural civilization,
في مدنيّة غنية ومتعددة الطوائف،
in one that is determined to liberate and fulfill
مدنية عازمة على التحرر والوفاء
the creative energies of its people.
بالطاقات الإبداعية لشعبها.
That's why India belongs at TED,
لأجل هذا الهند تنتمي لـ TED،
and that's why TED belongs in India.
ولأجل هذا TED ينتمي للهند.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)